<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" >
<article lang="en">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Me TV User Manual</title>
        <copyright>
            <year>2007</year>
            <year>2008</year>
            <year>2009</year>
            <holder>Michael Lamothe</holder>
        </copyright>
        <publisher>
            <publishername>Michael Lamothe</publishername>
        </publisher>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Legal Notice</title>
            <para>This file is part of <application>Me TV</application>. </para>
            <para><application>Me TV</application> is free software: you can redistribute it and/or
                modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free
                Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later
                version. </para>
            <para><application>Me TV</application> is distributed in the hope that it will be
                useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
                MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public
                License for more details. </para>
            <para>You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with
                    <application>Me TV</application>. If not, see <ulink
                    url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/">http://www.gnu.org/licenses/</ulink>.</para>
        </legalnotice>
        <author>
            <firstname>Michael</firstname>
            <surname>Lamothe</surname>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para><application>Me TV</application> is a digital television (DVB) viewer for GNOME.
                <application>Me TV</application> was developed for the modern digital lounge room
            with a PC for a media centre that is capable of normal PC tasks (web surfing, word
            processing and watching TV). It is not designed to be a full-blown media centre, such as
                <application>MythTV</application>, but will integrate well with an existing GNOME
            desktop.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Why <application>Me TV</application>?</title>
        <para>The name <application>Me TV</application> comes from Australian slang for "My TV".
            Hence, "it's TV for me computer" is Australian slang for "it's TV for my computer". The
            pattern can be followed for all instances of "My", such as "Me dog", "Me ute" and of
            course "Me beer".</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Features</title>
        <para> The following list contains the significant features of <application>Me
            TV</application>: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>GTK/GNOME interface</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Completely mouse driven</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Runs in system tray (see <link linkend="notification_icon">Notification
                            Icon</link>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Current and future program information (see <link linkend="epg_window">EPG
                            Window</link>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Instant Record</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Scheduled recordings (see <link
                            linkend="scheduled_recording">Scheduled Recordings</link>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Auto channel scan (see <link linkend="channel_scan_window">Channel Scan
                            window</link>)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Auto PID selection</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link linkend="audio_select">Audio select</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link linkend="network_broadcast">Network broadcast</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link linkend="dual_language">Dual language</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>DVB-T, DVB-C, DVB-S and ATSC support</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Double-click fullscreen</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link linkend="keyboard_shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Very simple installation and set up</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="channel_scan_window">
        <title>Channel Scan Window</title>
        <para>To use <application>Me TV</application> you need to have a channels file that lists
            the channels that you want Me TV to use. <application>Me TV</application> has a built-in
            scanner that allows you to automatically tune the stations available to you.</para>
        <para>When <application>Me TV</application> starts it will detect if you have a channels
            file (<filename>~/.me-tv/channels.conf</filename>). If a channel file does not exist
            then <application>Me TV</application> will ask if you would like to have one created. If
            you choose to create a channels file then <application>Me TV</application> will open the
            Channel Scan window asking you to select a region. If there is no region in the list
            that matches your region then you might have some luck with a region that is close to
            you. Double click a region (or select the region and click the
            <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button) to tell <application>Me TV</application> to begin
            the scan. During the scan, <application>Me TV</application> will show its progress in
            the text window, this process can take several minutes. When the scan completes the
            Channel Scan window will close automatically and <application>Me TV</application> will
            start.</para>
        <para>Digital television (DVB) allows television networks to supply many channels with the
            same (or similar) content so it's unlikely that you want Me TV to display all of them.
            To remove channels from <application>Me TV</application>, edit the
                <filename>~/.me-tv/channels.conf</filename> file and remove the channels that you
            don't want. If you would like <application>Me TV</application> to rescan channels then
            simply delete the <filename>~/.me-tv/channels.conf</filename> file and restart
                <application>Me TV</application>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="main_window">
        <title>Main Window</title>
        <para><application>Me TV</application>'s main window contains the main menu, the controls to
            drive <application>Me TV</application> (toolbar), video window, the EPG window, the
            program search bar and the status bar.</para>
        <sect2 id="main_menu">
            <title>Main Menu</title>
            <para>Many of the features of <application>Me TV</application> can be accessed through
                the main menu.</para>
            <sect3>
                <title>File</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem> exits <application>Me
                                TV</application>. If you are recording or you have a scheduled
                                recording then <application>Me TV</application> will confirm that
                                you want to exit. If you exit <application>Me TV</application> then
                                it will not be able to record a scheduled program. </para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>View</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Fullscreen</guimenuitem> toggles fullscreen
                            mode</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem> shows the <link
                                    linkend="preferences_window">Preferences window</link>. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Electronic Program Guide</guimenuitem> toggles the
                                display of the <link linkend="epg_window">EPG window</link>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Program Search</guimenuitem> enables the <link
                                    linkend="program_search_bar">Program search bar</link> below the
                                    <link linkend="epg_window">EPG window</link> allowing the user
                                to search for programs in the EPG.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Subtitles</guimenuitem> displays a list of detected
                                subtitle streams for the channel.</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Audio</title>
                <para>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Streams</guimenuitem> displays a list of detected
                                audio streams for the channel.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Mute</guimenuitem> toggles the audio. This will not
                                affect the audio in a recording or broadcast stream. </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para><guimenuitem>Dual Language</guimenuitem> the sub menu of this item
                                allows the user to select only the left or right audio channel to
                                come out both speakers. This is useful for people whose television
                                networks send the streams in two languages, one down the left and
                                the other down the right. (see <link linkend="dual_language">Dual
                                    language</link>)</para>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Help</title>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem> displays this user guide. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> shows the <link
                                linkend="about_window">About window</link>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="toolbar">
            <title>Toolbar</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guibutton>Record</guibutton> toggles recording.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guibutton>Mute</guibutton> toggles audio output. This will not affect the
                        audio in a recording or broadcast stream.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guibutton>Schedule</guibutton> opens the <link
                            linkend="scheduled_recordings_window">Scheduled recordings
                        window</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guibutton>Broadcast</guibutton> toggles <link linkend="network_broadcast"
                            >Network broadcast</link>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="video_window">
            <title>Video Window</title>
            <para>You can double click on the video window to toggle fullscreen mode. Upon entering
                fullscreen mode, all controls will be hidden. Right click on the video window to
                toggle the display of the controls in <application>Me TV</application>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="epg_window">
            <title>EPG Window</title>
            <para>The EPG (Electronic Program Guide) displays current and future program information
                sent from the television network. The EPG window is also used to change channels. It
                can be quickly accessed by right clicking on the video window.</para>
            <para>Click on a program to see the <link linkend="program_details_window">Program
                    details window</link> for that program or to schedule a recording for that
                program.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="status_bar">
            <title>Status Bar</title>
            <para>The status bar is used to let you know the status of Me TV. When viewing a channel
                it will display the channel name and current program title, if known. When
                recording, the status bar will display the filename of the file being recorded
            to.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="notification_icon">
        <title>The Notification Icon</title>
        <para>The <application>Me TV</application> notification icon is displayed in any
            notification area applet in the GNOME panel while <application>Me TV</application> is
            running. Left clicking on the icon will cause <application>Me TV</application> to mute
            and hide but it remains running. Recordings and scheduled recordings will continue to
            record when <application>Me TV</application> is in this state.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="program_details_window">
        <title>Program Details Window</title>
        <para>This window is displayed when a user clicks on a program in the <link
                linkend="epg_window">EPG window</link>. It displays a few details about the program
            and gives the user the option of scheduling the program for recording via the
                <guibutton>Record</guibutton> button. Clicking the <guibutton>Record</guibutton>
            button will open the <link linkend="scheduled_recording_window">Scheduled recording
                window</link>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="scheduled_recordings_window">
        <title>Scheduled Recordings Window</title>
        <para>The scheduled recordings window can be used to add and remove scheduled recordings
            from <application>Me TV</application>. Click the <guibutton>Add</guibutton> button to
            add an scheduled recording or select a scheduled recording from the list and click the
                <guibutton>Remove</guibutton> button.</para>
        <para>When a program is scheduled, <application>Me TV</application> will run in the system
            tray and wait for the program to start.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="scheduled_recording_window">
        <title>Scheduled Recording Window</title>
        <para>Not to be confused with the Scheduled Recording<emphasis>s</emphasis> window, this
            window allows you to set the values for a scheduled recording.<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Title</guilabel> is the title of the program, if available.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Description</guilabel> is the description of the program, if
                        available. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Start Time</guilabel> is the time that the program is scheduled
                        to start. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Duration</guilabel> is the duration of the program. </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Clicking the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button will open the <link
                linkend="scheduled_recordings_window">Scheduled recordings window</link> with the
            newly scheduled recording in the list of scheduled recordings.</para>
        <para>When a program is scheduled, <application>Me TV</application> will run in the system
            tray and wait for the program to start.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="preferences_window">
        <title>Preferences Window</title>
        <para>The Preferences window can be used to configure <application>Me TV</application>.<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Recording directory</guilabel> is the directory where
                            <application>Me TV</application> will save its recorded files.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Record extra before</guilabel> is the default number of minutes
                        that will be added to the start of the recording.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Record extra after</guilabel> is the default number of minutes
                        that will be added to the end of the recording.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Recording type</guilabel> is used to specify the video format of
                            <application>Me TV</application>'s recorded files. The MPEG TS format is
                        best for storing multiple audio streams and subtitles. When using MPEG PS
                            <application>Me TV</application> will not be able to record subtitles
                        however you might find that this format is supported by more players.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>EPG span hours</guilabel> is the number of hours that the <link
                            linkend="epg_window">EPG window</link> will span on one page.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Broadcast port</guilabel> is the network port used when
                        broadcasting over the network.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>EPG encoding</guilabel> is used to specify how to process text
                        elements from the DVB stream. The DVB stream will, in most cases, tell
                            <application>Me TV</application> which encoding it is using however some
                        countries, like the Czech Republic, use a different encoding for the EPG
                        information. If you are having difficulties displaying non-English
                        characters then changing this setting may help.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Video driver</guilabel> specifies the xine video output driver
                        to use. Sometimes the xine engine is unable to display video output properly
                        because of the users video setup. Changing this setting may help with this
                        issue.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Deinterlace type</guilabel> is used to specify type of
                        deinterlacing. You may find that changing this setting improves the video
                        depending on your setup.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Start minimised in tray</guilabel> tells <application>Me
                        TV</application> to startup in the notification area when it starts. This
                        setting can be useful if you get <application>Me TV</application> to start
                        automatically when you log in.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Always on top</guilabel> tells <application>Me TV</application>
                        to stay on top of other windows on the desktop.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>Fullscreen workaround</guilabel> addresses an issue on some
                            <application>Compiz</application> setups that won't let you show a popup
                        window on top of another window that is in fullscreen mode. This setting
                        will temporarily take you out of fullscreen while viewing a popup window and
                        then return you to fullscreen mode after closing the popup window.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><guilabel>PID workaround</guilabel> has been implemented because there has
                        been a report of the PID auto-detection not selecting the right PID. This is
                        a temporary workaround in-case the issue arises again on someone's computer
                        after release. This feature may be removed in the next release of
                            <application>Me TV</application> (currently 0.5.10).</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="about_window">
        <title>About Window</title>
        <para>The About window shows legal information, contributors and further information about
                <application>Me TV</application>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="features">
        <title>Features Explained</title>
        <para>This is a brief explanation of some of the features of <application>Me
            TV</application>.</para>
        <sect2 id="keyboard_shortcuts">
            <title>Keyboard Shortcuts</title>
            <para>Many of the features of <application>Me TV</application> can be accessed using the
                keyboard. The following list of keys (uppercase or lowercase) can be used on the
                    <link linkend="main_window">Main window</link>.<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>A</keysym> toggles <link linkend="auto_surf">Auto
                        surf</link>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>B</keysym> toggles <link linkend="network_broadcast">Network
                                broadcast</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>E</keysym> toggles the visibility of the <link
                                linkend="epg_window">EPG window</link></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>F</keysym> toggles fullscreen</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>H</keysym> hides all the controls</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>M</keysym> toggles mute</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><keysym>R</keysym> toggles recording</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="scheduled_recording">
            <title>Scheduled Recording</title>
            <para><application>Me TV</application> is able to schedule future programs to be
                recorded. When a program is due to be recorded, <application>Me TV</application>
                will change to the channel and start recording.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="audio_select">
            <title>Audio Select</title>
            <para>Some stations transmit television in multiple audio languages. <application>Me
                TV</application> allows you to select different audio languages from the
                    <guimenuitem>Audio/Streams</guimenuitem> menu item. <application>Me
                TV</application> will remember (until you log out) which audio stream you selected
                the next time you select the channel.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="dual_language">
            <title>Dual Language</title>
            <para>Some television networks transmit television programs in multiple languages by
                sending different languages down the left and right channels of the audio stream.
                Dual language allows you to play either the left or right audio channel through both
                speakers. Dual language is available through the <guimenuitem>Audio/Dual
                Language</guimenuitem> menu item.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="network_broadcast">
            <title>Network Broadcast</title>
            <para>The network broadcast feature allows users to broadcast their television stream
                over a network making it possible for other computers to receive television. Digital
                television uses a lot of data so this feature is not recommended for networks that
                are slower than 100 Mbit/s. There are many players that can be used for a client including:<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <application>xine</application>
                            <command>xine udp://224.0.1.2:2005</command>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <application>mplayer</application>
                            <command>mplayer udp://224.0.1.2:2005</command>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <application>VLC</application>
                            <command>vlc udp://@224.0.1.2:2005</command>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="feedback">
        <title>Feedback</title>
        <para>If you have comments about this manual or Me TV then please email me at
                <email>michael.lamothe@gmail.com</email>. Bugs and new features are welcome at the
                <ulink url="https://launchpad.net/me-tv">project website</ulink>.</para>
    </sect1>
</article>
